Guide to the First Union Baptist Church of Christ at Farmerville records, 1819-1899.
First Union Baptist Church of Christ at Farmerville records, 1819-1899
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
First Union Baptist Church of Christ at Farmerville records, 1819-1899.
6068
First Union Baptist Church of Christ at Farmerville (Interlaken, N.Y.)
2 reels microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
One volume of covenant meeting minutes (1819-1894); one volume of annual meeting to elect trustees minutes (1825-1899); issues of the American Baptist Magazine and Missionary Intelligencer (Volume IV, no. 5; Volume III, no. 4); and minutes of the twentieth-seventh annual meeting of the Seneca Baptist Association (1848). Covenant meeting minutes document a split in 1828, accounts of revivals, church discipline and doctrine.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
This church was organized as the Baptist Church of Farmer Village on November 22, 1819 with Elder John Lewis as the pastor. A house of worship costing $3,000 was built in 1823. In 1828 a disagreement among members caused some to leave and join the Dutch Reformed Church at Farmerville. This rift was repaired in 1830 and the church called itself the Union Baptist Church thereafter, to signify the union of the two groups. Revivals led to rapid growth in the church's membership prior to the Civil War, and a new church, costing $8,000 was built in 1861. An unauthenticated source says that Captain Winfield Scott recruited 130 men from the church's Sunday School to serve in the Civil War and that their band played at Harper's Ferry and at Appomatox. The church was a member of the Seneca Association.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection contains one volume of Covenant meeting minutes (1819-1894), which contains membership lists for 1819 and 1830, one volume of trustee's records (1825-1899) which contains an account of the church's incorporation in 1824 and annual meeting minutes, The American Baptist Magazine, Vol. Ill no. 4 (July 1821) and Vol. IV no. 5, (Sept. 1823), and "Minutes of the Twenty-Seventh Annual Meeting of the Seneca Baptist Association" in 1848.
SUBJECTS
Names:
First Union Baptist Church of Christ at Farmerville (Interlaken, N.Y.); Lewis, John.; Baptist Church of Farmer Village (Interlaken, N.Y.); Seneca Baptist Association (N.Y.); Union Baptist Church (Interlaken, N.Y.)
Titles:
American Baptist Magazine.
Subjects:
Baptists--New York (State)--Interlaken.; Baptists--Government.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Interlaken.; Baptist church buildings.; Revivals--New York (State)--Interlaken.
Places:
Interlaken (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Seneca County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Covenant Meeting Minute Book, 1819-1894
  Labeled "Church Clerk's Book". Contains the articles of faith of the church, meeting minutes, membership lists, and the church covenant. Items of note and approximate locations in the book follow:
  - Page
    Articles of Faith. The script version is covered by the printed version.
  - Page 3, Oct. 18, 1819
    Meeting to decide on the propriety of founding a church.
  - Page 4, Nov. 22, 1819
    Church formed. 2 deeds for a pew from the trustees to Jeremiah Rappleye, the church clerk, dated Feb. 25, 1828 and Apr. 30, 1825.
  - Page 48, Dec. 9, 1824
    Discussion of church policy on fund raising.
  - Page 76, May 3, 1828
    Voted that the sisters not have an equal right with, the male members to vote in matters of discipline.
  - Page 77, May 24, 1828
    Church splits.
  - Page 88, July 4, 1829
    Anti-Masonry resolution. Resolution to aid foreign missions.
  - Page 90-93, October 1829
    Attempts at reconciliation.
  - Page 94
    Conference called. (Note: From pages 77-96 are the records of one group, then the records pass into the hands of the other group who recount their side of the story.)
  - Page 96
    Declaration of the seceeders.
  - Page 100, Aug. 20, 1828
    Account of the conference called.
  - Page 109, Aug. 7, 1830
    Splinter group voted to join the Seneca Association.
  - Page 117, Oct. 19, 1830
    Voted to hold a protracted meeting on the first Sunday in October.
  - Page 118, Oct. 19, 1830
    Report of the meeting.
  - Page 122, July 6, 1833
    Voted to have the females hold a prayer meeting.
  - Page 123, Aug. 25, 1833
    Plans for a protracted meeting in October.
  - Page 123, Nov. 2, 1833
  - Page 129, Oct. 4, 1834
    Protracted meeting planned.
  - Page 131, Feb. 7, 1835
    Voted to accept as members those who have been baptised by pedobaptist ministers.
  - Page 141, Dec. 3, 1836
    Voted to hold a protracted meeting with Elder King.
  - Page 142, Jan. 8, 1837
    Met to organize the American Baptist Bible Society.
  - Page 142, Feb. 4, 1837
    Formed an Auxiliary Bible Society.
  - Page 148, Feb. 1838
    Report of a protracted meeting.
  - Page 164, Jan. 16, 1841
  - Page 187, Jan. 16, 1844
    Bro. expelled for embracing the Doctrine of Universal Salvation.
  - Page 203, Oct. 3, 1846
    Voted to circulate a subscription to buy a lot and build a parsonage.
  - Page 211-212, March-Apr. 1877
    Many baptisms.
  - Page 224-228, Jan. -March 1854
    Protracted meeting led by 0. Montague
  - Page 226-247
  - Page 257-258, Apr. 6, 1861
    Discussion of building a new church.
  - Page 260, Feb. 25, 1862
    New house of worship dedicated.
  - Page 279, Dec. 5, 1868
    Voted to have Bro. George Balcom come and assist vith a protracted meeting.
  - Page 278-280, Dec.-Jan. 1869
    Revival.
  - Page 281, July 16, 1869
    Sick man is baptised at home.
  - Page 294, 1876 Feb. 11, 1894
    Pagination ends. Last entry. Key to membership list.
  - 2 p.
    Membership as of formation.
  - Feb. 10, 1830
    Membership list (after split). Church Covenant.
- Trustee's Record Book, Sept. 10, 1825-Feb. 1, 1899
  This volume includes minutes of yearly meeting to elect trustees and an account of the incorporation of the church on April 3, 1824 at the beginning of the volume, Items of note include:
  - Feb. 24, 1847
    Resolved to buy a lot and build a parsonage on it.
  - 1854
    No meeting.
  - 1859
  - April l86l
    Voted to tear down the old house of worship and build a new one.
  - 1862
    Discussion of pew rental.
  - 1863
    Account of the church's financial situation and copy of the subscription list. (Note: After 1863 financial reports are included in the minutes.)
  - 1869
  - 1880
    Resolved to call the church the Baptist Church of Farmer Village.
- The American Baptist Magazine and Missionary Intelligencer
  Vol. III, No. 4, July 1821. Page 132 contains the report of a revival in Camillus, Onadago (sic.) County, New York in 1818.
- The American Baptist Magazine and Missionary Intelligencer
  Vol. IV, No. 5, Sept. 1823.
- Minutes of the Twenty-Seventh Annual Meeting of the Seneca Baptist Association
  For 1848. (Aug. 30, 31) held with the Baptist Church of Trumansburg, N.Y. Lists churches, clerks, delegates, number received by letter, dropped, died, membership, statistical information and correspondence with other associations with meeting minutes.